howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guest is phillip howard phillip
is the director of the oxford internet
institute
and a professor of internet studies at
oxford
he investigates the impact of digital
media on political life
around the world and he's a frequent
contributor and commenter on global
media and political affairs
howard's research has demonstrated how
new information technologies
are used in both civil engagement and
social control in countries around the
world
hi jim thanks for having me yeah this
would be good this is really interesting
stuff
we're going to talk today mostly about
howard's new book
the lie machines how to save democracy
from troll armies deceitful robots
junk news operations and political
operatives
howard's got a cherry job can you
imagine having the job
of professor of internet studies at
oxford holy moly
it's treatment yeah it's like how could
it be any better right like the perfect
job right
to talk about timely in addition to this
particular book
he has written several other books on
the impact of internet and technology in
society including one that i'm going to
dig into
because it just looked interesting i
looked at the brief write-up on it
called pax technica how the internet of
things may set us free or
lock us up and of course as often in the
world the answer is most likely both
right none of this stuff just cuts one
way so let's hop into it
you know from the preface of the book
this is an interesting place to start
you said this book is about the teams of
people who do the work of embedding new
information technologies into our
political lives but use those technical
systems to
misinform us distract us and discourage
sensible deliberation you know this ties
into something we fairly often talk
about on the show
which group of people i work with we
call it bad faith
discourse it really is a plague right
and as you also point out in the book
there's a direct quote
our most valuable resource possible in a
democracy
is our attention and as a person with
significant background and cognitive
science i often point out that frankly
we
are our attention and you combine
bad faith discourse with hijacking our
attention
and we're really talking about a plague
something that is really undermining our
ability to be who we are
yeah and there's interesting ways the
covet plague has this informational side
to it as well i mean it's making
many of us sick and it's the source of a
lot of
health health misinformation right
there's a lot of health and
health misinformation around covet that
it's just confusing people
it's getting people to take risks they
wouldn't normally take and it's yeah
it's part of the big problem yeah it's
really been quite astounding to me and i
would say that
what's been particularly astounding and
disturbing
about the covid misinformation and bad
faith discourse i don't know it's bad
faith discourse or rampant insanity
is that even intelligent well-educated
people
a significant percentage of them seem to
be adopting
all kinds of seemingly ridiculous ideas
it may well be that whatever
you know the social media phenomenon has
been doing to our ability to sense make
has reached some level of criticality
undermining trust in general has gotten
to the point that people
have no ability to make sense at all
anymore and we're going to dig into that
in some detail
i think an important qualification for
our discussion about the book is to be
clear to our audience that
you're basically talking pretty much
only about organized
paid disinformation and you don't really
delve into some of the things we've
talked about in the show before which is
the emerging unofficial sector
of political discourse some of it in bad
faith you know the
4chan 8chan thing meme wars etc
but this is a very important subdomain
of bad faith discourse that which is
organized and paid for by governments
political actors lobbyists
etc right and and in a sense both
both domains feed off each other right
if a campaign can get a bunch of
volunteers to
generate a story that that attacks or
some negative campaigning that attacks a
an opponent you know they'll do subtle
things to encourage it
and formally under the law they're not
supposed to coordinate a campaign
shouldn't coordinate its
strategy with those volunteer groups but
it's not uncommon for a major candidate
to have
friends who do things under the table
for them
in advance of the same same agenda or
the same goal of getting elected
so they the volunteers definitely can
work in tandem with
the paid consultants yeah and also i
would say not even the volunteers just
the
players out on the net one of the things
we've explored in the past
is how the memetic payloads are often
created by
independents or out in the chans often
and then they circulate up to
reddit to the donald which just just
recently got taken down by reddit but is
amazingly rapidly reappeared as an
independent platform with
as much traffic as it had on reddit
which is something worth thinking about
and then the memes get upregulated on
the donald these are the pro-trump
memes and then they get picked up by
breitbart then they get picked up by fox
news and then
trump repeats them a few of them and so
there's a cycle
that is basically not driven by these
operatives we're talking about but is
accelerated by them so that's an
important other part of the architecture
i would say
which we're probably not going to get
into in great depth but we'll talk about
how
things like bots can facilitate that
another
sort of definitional thing before we
drop into some more details
is again from the preface what connects
these arguments is that first and
foremost
politics is a socio-technical system
constituted by both ideology and
technology
maybe you could explain a little bit i
think that was you did a very good job
of it in the book about talking about
how it's naive
to think of technology as now a
completely separate domain it really is
kind of part and parcel of how we do
politics
talk a little bit about that yeah it's
it's um
it's about two different platforms uh
right it's about the social system that
that includes these campaign lobbyists
or troll farms in russia
and there this can be small groups
they're always formal groups right so
they have
job ads and performance bonuses and
secretaries and telephones and office
space
this isn't about lone wolf opera
operatives this is about formal
organizations
and then the other part of the lie
machine is the technical the algorithms
that
that take content generated by those
organizations
and deliver it to your inbox your social
media feed
your twitter feed um and those
algorithms
help ensure that it's relevant content
you're likely to respond to
how it's tailored in some way for you
and i don't think you can tell the story
of modern politics without some
appreciation of the technical side the
technical platforms and the uh
the social organization of it all it's
it's one big complex system and it's a
global system right
it's not just uh not just based within
the us it
involves political players around the
world
yeah i think that's one of the things
that's probably mostly new at least
inbound into the west is to the degree
to which
state actors or closely affiliated the
state actors are taking a role
now to be honest the west has
manipulated elections all around the
world since the 50s so in some sense
it's turnabout but
you know the relatively low cost and
anonymity that the
networks provide has actually made us
eat some of our own
food that we've been doing by more brute
force methods for a long time
yeah i think that's one of the big
surprises that um there's actually
multiple governments who are trying to
target
voters in the us and canada australia
and the uk
i think for many years russia had some
interest in
moving public opinion in the u.s and
china didn't seem to have much interest
but in the last two years china china
really has started pushing out more
more propaganda more messaging more
media messaging
in english and on social media platforms
that chinese citizens can't actually use
so it's it's pretty clearly
what we call computational propaganda
directed at voters in the west
yep and not just china too even iran
apparently is in the game right
we're not sure to what degree and
probably anti-trump
but they're playing too well one of the
interesting things about
doing this research is that is is
finding how some
governments some regimes are actually
not very good at it
very not very good at doing
misinformation so i think we've caught
organizations in venezuela and iran
india and pakistan they all have little
iras little internet research agencies
that try to copy what
what the russian government set up
perhaps around 2012
but they don't tend to have a big impact
they tend to mostly be involved with
twitter
they tend to get caught and exposed and
you know most of the creativity frankly
happens amongst the pr
firms in the west or or with the russian
russian information operations
yeah china too i wouldn't underestimate
china i mean they have a lot of skill
and they often do blunder at first but
they also learn pretty rapidly
so i suspect that we'll see china as a
bigfoot in this in the years ahead
now let's talk a little bit about what
differentiates these social media
platforms
from at least qualitatively similar
forms of targeting in the past i mean
we've always had targeted direct mail i
happen to know richard vigory who was
the inventor of modern direct mail back
in the
late 70s and he had an incredible you
know data operation
bought micro targeting information from
axiom
and some of the other data aggregators
and you know a big part of the reagan
political machine was essentially fueled
by richard vigory and his
mastery of direct mail then a little
later there's
the email thing was pretty funny my
mother and her
republican friends were passing around
some of the most absurd shit imaginable
by the mid 90s right and of course we've
always had
less fine-grained micro targeting than
babel today on things like tv
advertising for politics
you know famously at least in the united
states almost all of the political
advertising goes into the so-called
battleground
states a handful of states and which is
thought the election will turn and
further
they target specific geographic areas on
specific
tv networks and then even specific shows
so
we've always had a fair amount totally
since the 60s
a fair amount of targeting and such what
in your mind makes
the world of the social media platforms
qualitatively different than what we had
in the past
one of the big differences between
direct mail campaigns
and the modern computational propaganda
machine
is the narrow targeting and i think it's
fabulous that you you know richard vigor
in his his work
for reagan that was big innovation at
the time right that was a
a system that took voter registration
files and address records
sometimes they were kept on punch cards
right and fed through
the computers that needed punch used
punch cards just to calculate what kinds
of letters should go to what kinds of
prospective donors and prospective
voters
most of that messaging was was pretty
broad right pretty general it wasn't it
wasn't a b
tested the way a modern ad is on
facebook right
so if we look at some of the big
campaigns if a
candidate for office or a lobbyist has
enough money they'll produce a couple of
different ads
they'll test them to see which ads play
well they'll test them to see which ads
play well for men which ads play for
women
behavioral researchers tell us that
women respond well to a deep voice and
men respond well to a high-pitched
female voice and
there's all these other things that have
to do with you know frankly skin tone
and look
and appearance and age
that'll make it possible to customize an
ad
so that you get a message from someone
who looks like you
and that kind of narrow casting delivery
is a pretty big difference from
from what we used to get uh over tv and
you know before political campaigning in
um in the us started playing with direct
mail and
direct mail databases most of the
political messaging
was only ever broadcast around on
election day
or during major wars and then it was
mostly the
big governments that would spend big
money on political advertising in
significant ways
now it's incredibly cheap right
relatively inexpensive
to run some ads to buy ads yourself
to do this a b testing that i was just
talking about or
or to run a basic campaign on social
media doesn't cost a lot of money
and that's exciting it's exciting in the
sense that it's democratizing we all
have access to the technology we can all
express ourselves politically
and but it means that there's a lot more
peripheral voices and extremist voices
and sensational content because to get
those clicks right to grab somebody's
attention
online you need to use potty mouth words
and
lots of exclamation marks and have crazy
slightly altered
images that's what makes a modern
campaign
grab attention yeah of course it is true
that in the richard vigory and the
direct mail world there was a lot of a b
testing in fact abcd testing typically i
actually ran a business back in the 80s
that
was principally driven by direct mail
and we did a 16-part test
actually and so a b testing itself
isn't new and i know for sure vigory was
doing it
but rather it's the fact that you can go
from you know sixteen to two thousand
right you can test two thousand ads
simultaneously with subtly different
wording subtly different coloring
positioning etc
and unlike direct mail the cycle time to
test and learn was about two months that
was the real problem right
you could only test a couple of times
during an election cycle
with internet advertising today it's
literally real time
you can start to down regulate your
spend on the ads that aren't performing
within minutes and then up regulate the
ones that are testing
it's actually quite interesting and as
you talk about the democraticization
that's interesting that you mentioned
that because
just for fun i went through the process
on facebook and qualified to be a
political advertiser i don't know about
three months ago i don't know why i did
i just i tell you why because i was
getting
some of my facebook ads for my podcasts
were getting disapproved i go what the
hell
and i'd contacted them and they said
well you know this could be interpreted
as political even though i don't
generally talk about political topics
per se more scientific
or social trends i said all right well
what do i need to do to qualify to be a
political advertiser and so they told me
and i went through the process it was
fairly straightforward so now i am a
registered facebook political advertiser
and what kind of questions did they ask
the main thing was that
i think this is probably correct at
least if you take a free speech
perspective which i do
which is they basically wanted to
ratchet up the quality of
my identity to make sure they knew who i
actually was so friends i had to send a
copy of my driver's license
i had to give them a physical address
they sent a hard copy
i think was a postcard or something with
a code on it which i then had to log
back in
and give that code number so it was
essentially a ratcheting up of the
quality of my real name identity and
being able to
you know link it firmly with an actual
physical address
and so yeah it was a low barrier but it
was enough to
probably make it more difficult for bad
actors to be able to advertise on
facebook and as i understand this is new
this did not exist in 2016 but it's
something that they have put in place
the last
couple of years to at least attempt to
trim back some of the abuse of their
political advertising system
right and now that you've got permission
are you placing more overtly political
ads
no i have not only occasionally do i
advertise my
podcast turns out it's not really a very
effective advertising medium for
podcasts much better is within podcast
apps themselves but i might as we get
closer to the election just for fun i
might run some experimental ads and just
see what happens
kind of interested in the phenomenon
it's interesting a lot of the firms in a
lot of
countries have decided to stop carrying
political ads altogether
because it's it's too hard it's too
difficult for a firm to
um monitor who's a political actor and
who's not and
and the reporting requirements um so you
know there's multiple countries where
facebook and google they've just decided
to stop taking
political political money for political
ads
i'm not sure that's a good solution
because i do think that it's um
important for political candidates you
know candidates running for office
to be able to advertise what they stand
for and it shouldn't be just about
raising money they should be able to get
their ideas out into the public sphere
and i think media has an obligation a
social obligation
to carry some of those ads so i sort of
i'd rather see facebook and
take political ads and then do the due
diligence to make sure that they're
high quality from from real political
actors
and saying you know things that are
constructive and not hate speech or
um you know nasty and destructive for
public life
yeah that's interesting that what is
that line right
what is the content line and you know i
have to admit it's a free speech
fairly much fundamentalist i'm always
suspicious of
attempts to you know constrain speech
and i'm actually even skeptical of the
hate concept because i've noticed
already
it's expanding to become a politicized
hammer for one side to hit the other you
know for instance
you'll see people referring to good
faith commentary about limiting
immigration
as hate speech or the famous case in the
united states where a very religious
baker refused to bake a cake for a gay
marriage
you can disagree with his perspective on
it but it's not necessarily hate
and so again i'm suspicious of these
broad categories like hey i think you
got to get much more detailed about
behaviors but
we'll get into that but before we do
let's go into a key concept which again
is fairly broad
in your book which is a political lie
you define it much more broadly than say
the catholic sin
of telling a lie and including you know
being incendiary et cetera
give us a little bit about your
definition of a political lie
well for me a political lies is
an untruth something that's patently
false that's put
in the service of some ideology so it's
it's um
an apparent a bald-faced lie that's um
got some agenda political agenda behind
it
um and every week we see new examples of
of what these things look like
i think that the real tough thing about
studying misinformation over the last
few years
has been that the types of
misinformation are getting really really
subtle
so um just last week one of the big
incidents for the for those of us who
watch this stuff involved a string
of some 20 or 30 fake commentator
profiles
who have been successfully filing
commentary essays with an agency called
newsmax and the washington examiner so
these are experts
who were talking about the middle east
but they were
fake personas they had particular
perspectives on particular countries in
the region
but those news outlets didn't do
anything to check who these
these people were and whether they were
real or not it turns out they were not
real
so so there's an example of a very
a very subtle campaign strategy that
took a long time to catch
that was coordinated and you know lasted
for months
involved let's see here involved 19 fake
personas
with 90 opinion pieces and 46
publications over the last over the last
year
so that some of these operations can get
quite large
and you know there's different kinds of
lies at the
different ends of the political spectrum
and i think there's uh
unfortunately the variety of political
lies is growing
who was behind that did somebody find
out this was something reported in the
daily beast so i don't remember that
they
they located it i i think there's um
there were some well-placed articles
critical of the government of qatar
and so and supportive of tough sanctions
against iran
and these are particularly conservative
news websites
i don't remember from the coverage who
they if they could attribute blame
and this is one of the other tricks for
doing this kind of research it's very
difficult
for us as independent researchers to
verify who's responsible and one of the
only
data sets i've ever played with of
verified trolled accounts
are the data sets that facebook turned
over from the 2016 election
on known russian fake facebook
users who were accounts that were
clearly set up from st petersburg
and designed to pretend to be fake
american voters there's about three and
a half thousand of them and they
the firm gave these da they gave this
data set to the us senate
select committee on intelligence um and
the u.s
select committee on intelligence gave it
to us at oxford university to analyze
and that's
that's one of the few data sets of
verified troll accounts that we've
played with
it's very hard to know it's very hard as
an outsider
to know who's behind these fake accounts
yeah that's one of the things that's a
little bit different in this new world
though if facebook is actually verifying
who runs political ads the ads they can
track but as you point out in your book
perhaps it's the junk news that's
actually more
powerful than the ads however
interestingly this
example you just gave you know a likely
suspect would be
saudi arabia i suspect right if qatar
and saudi arabia are famously
antagonistic
and if it's anti-iran that would sort of
point in that direction which is kind of
interesting
let's go back to this political lie
concept a little bit in the book you
actually give a much broader
definition than just an untruth for
instance i'll read this direct quote
from the book
content that promotes undue skepticism
negative emotions
contrarian views for the sake of
teaching the controversy
or text and video messages that bring
anxiety or
aversion to dialogue and new evidence
also fall into the broad category of
political lies
could you say a little bit more about
that much broader definition
well so one of the things that's useful
about that definition is that it also
captures
visual misinformation which is something
that's
we didn't have as much of in 2016 and
visual misinformation is
slightly doctored images or images taken
out of context
and visual information visual misinfo
can
can bring home the punch line of a
political lie but
but itself is you know difficult to
verify and difficult to catch
in a systematic way so if misinformation
is designed
to provoke you to ask a question that
doesn't need to be asked it's having an
impact
for example when the covet
really emerged in the u.s as a
phenomenon
there was a several prominent public
figures wanted to
call covid the wuhan virus
and the chinese government responded by
tasking its its national media agencies
to um ask the question about whether
maybe the virus had originated in a lab
in colorado
and the virus didn't originate in the
lab in colorado and it's not
it's it wasn't born out in the lab
anywhere but
the the strategy the the rhetorical way
of presenting this political lie
is was has been to write news articles
that say and then ask the question
where the headline is did the virus
emerge from a lab
question mark right and then you get you
find a doctor i think it was a doctor
from northern italy who would ask the
question
and there's no evidence but um simply
asking the question
allows you to explore take some pictures
of labs in colorado
and paint a story of how other
viruses maybe originate in labs through
a variety of experiments
so these big these big arcs these big
false stories can emerge
not when somebody makes an overt lie
the chinese government never said that
the the virus originated in a lab in the
united states
but their media agency asked these
provocative questions and found a few
experts who are asked you know other
questions and that's what creates
this this element of misinformation
around the origins
of covert 19. yeah so that's a very
important i think distinction that we're
talking here not just about
explicit lies but we're talking about
using
manipulative messages hooks to emotion
as you say
provocative images to insert misleading
information
into people's minds even without
actually explicitly lying
i think this very important distinction
and comes down to a lot of what makes
our current social media perhaps a
mismatch for our cognitive capabilities
which we'll talk about here
in a little bit let's go on to the next
thing this is really the main model of
your book
which is you take the concept of the
political lie and then you
posit that there is a lie machine
there's a
three-part system that you've identified
where lies are essentially
industrialized
and put to work for political state
actors
lobbyists etc how don't you lay out the
concept of the lie machine and what the
three parts are
and maybe talk a little bit about what
the implications of that are
well as we talked about earlier the lie
machine has a social aspect and a
technical aspect the technical side is
the
algorithms social media algorithms or
search algorithms
that deliver content to you and the
social system is the
small groups of people who make this
stuff up or the politicians who pay for
it and commission it
or the lobbyists who spread it around
and and fake news journalists who
turn it into longer news stories but
when they produce this content
or distribute this content there's sort
of three cycles there's a there's a
production stage and it's the very it's
the very first stage where
you work out what kinds of messages you
want to push or who your target is
which politician you want to take down a
few notches or which politician you want
to promote
that production stage often involves the
testing of messages
and creating a narrative or a long story
and making up a long background so that
if somebody searches
they might find a little history to the
misinformation
after the production stage there's a
dissemination stage and that's simply
about
well as we've discussed it's about
paying for the ads
it's about getting a an organic network
of humans to
to distribute stories across twitter or
instagram and that distribution stage
it usually involves trying to game
social media algorithms
trying to get them to push a story
further than it would normally go or to
take advantage of
maybe how youtube catalogs entries
to make sure that if somebody searches
for keywords around your topic
your story or you your fake news article
your fake news video will get to the top
of the search results
after that dissemination phase there's
sort of a marketing phase where there's
a separate group of people a different
group of people who
who promote the story and carry it over
many many months
exacerbate it as you said push it down
into back into 4chan or 8chan
where it can get new energy and get
relaunched and sometimes it's difficult
to anticipate
which stories which fake news stories
junk news stories will actually do well
in the public sphere and sometimes the
vast majority of the stories
die they don't go very far uh but then
you know six months down the road
somebody picks up a nugget of something
that was forgotten and runs with it
again
so this is the sort of aftermarket of um
taking stories that have been produced
and disseminated
and turning them into a long-term
long-term part of a public conversation
so production dissemination and
marketing
yep i think the part that was the
biggest illumination to me
i should not have been surprised was how
the marketing component has now really
come to the fore
and i suppose it's frankly not that much
different than richard vigory and his
direct mail marketing but now apply to
the affordances
that have been enabled by the social
media platforms
now are these marketing firms are they
parts of like big
marketing companies you know the global
ad agencies are they typically
independents
they're a little bit of both i'd say
that the big ad agencies
the big pr firms do have units now that
specialize in
this kind of tool kit and i remember
seeing another story from buzzfeed
where the author the journalist reported
that
how many of the contemporary
misinformation campaigns we know about
actually have their origins in a in a
major pr firm
not a foreign government so this is this
is now
it's it's now it's an increasingly
common service that the pr firms will
will offer that said
the most aggressive and manipulative
firms
that do this work tend to be overseas
in the book i write about one in poland
and another one in brazil
they work for politicians um political
clients and lobbyists
in fact there for one of them actually
the one in poland the primary customers
were not politicians
the primary customers were
pharmaceuticals firms
and and the example that was given to us
was that
the firm would hire 10 000 fake
facebook users to
be sick in some way to to have trouble
managing their migraines
and and and say that say as much over
facebook and then they would hire 10
other 10 000 other
fake facebook accounts users to go in
and have a new medicine
for managing migraines and then these
these fake users would have
conversations with each other on public
boards right
about the exciting new medicine and the
ways of um managing migraines that
this one this farm these pharmaceutical
firms had come up with
so this is not it's not always about
politicians
and some of the most innovative work
comes from
regular firms that want to push their
products but then political campaign
managers will take the good tools and
use them for political campaigning
now this actually hits on something i
have my notes later but let's talk about
it now
which is information that's presented as
if it's coming organically from
real people hits people in a different
way than what is obviously paid
advertising
you know one of the things that we can
say about humans is we may not have had
good defenses against advertising in
1890 when mass advertising first started
but we know a relatively high level of
skepticism
i see a political ad on tv my first
assumption is it's manipulative horse
shit right
but if what appears to be a good faith
conversation between
actual people on a public board we think
about that differently could you talk
about that a little bit
yeah and i i like your expression good
faith conversation because
many of us have faith that the internet
is bringing you know for a long first
decade maybe the internet brought us
mostly truths it brought us access to
information we didn't have before
um there were a lot of free speech
values behind
the construction of the internet and a
lot of reasons to be excited and hopeful
about the impact of the internet the
role of the internet in democracy and
liberation
so i think we we tend to trust
information that comes over
digital media more than we trust
information that comes over broadcast
now operationally that means it's easy
to take advantage of people
right if you if you can slip something
in to the social media
social media stream and you can get your
uh you know one of
somebody's family members or friends to
forward something without actually
reading it
then that information comes to us
through our networks of family and
friends and and we we tend to trust it
more that's always one of the cognitive
biases we were hitting and you were
hitting at earlier
we tend to trust information that comes
from people we already know
a little bit more than stuff that comes
from people we we
don't know who aren't like us yep and so
hence the the real deep play for these
lyme machine people is to you know get
things out of circulations that look
like
obvious paid placements or even
journalistic
point of view things like you go to
breitbart you know it's right-wing
crankery
but if some people start spouting that
same line themselves it's likely to slip
in under our discrimination radar to
quite a good degree
yeah in the biz we call it the organic
content it's the content that comes from
volunteers from real people
maybe it has a typo or a spelling
mistake in it
it looks it's not clean copy written by
a professional
you know professional communications
person
that's the stuff that we tend to respond
more to
and in an interesting way this i think
there's actually become
a kind of a different style to russian
state
propaganda and from chinese state
propaganda
on this question of style so for example
most of the
russian profile russian state-backed
profiles that we've studied actually
have a long history
and they they make posts about flowers
and soccer scores and
you know soap operas and they they have
a long what we call legend they're
around for
years and then they start talking about
politics
right so they get into your social media
networks you don't really notice them or
you don't think of them as
as plants obviously but then they
suddenly start
going on strong for one political
candidate and that seems to be the
russian
state style of producing misinformation
the chinese style government style and
because it's really just emerged in the
last year and year or two
is a lot more fast and blunt they'll
simply buy
twenty thousand fake twitter users and
the the
user accounts will be all numbers and
they won't have any pictures
right and they're they're create they
were created yesterday
and then they suddenly they will wake up
and push push a message or echo
something that
the state media broadcaster is so the on
the one hand you've got the chinese
style which is by volume
right huge numbers of fake accounts that
most of us would spot
as being fake accounts uh and then the
much more subtle
long long legend long story line
accounts that um
that the russians have been been
grooming for a much longer period
that's interesting and my guess would be
that per unit of
posting the russian style would be
vastly more effective
however quantity versus quality one
would have to do the research to
determine which is the better overall
strategy
and the chinese are not stupid so if
they continuing to do this
it must work at least for some segment
of their audience
yes that would be a great research
question i don't know which one's more
effective
i think you know one of the one of the
challenges for trying to get
a political lie into circulation
is is going is is getting the story
getting the nugget to go from something
that your bots
and your your trolls are trading around
to having a real human or or a prominent
prominent hollywood actor or a political
figure to tweet
and that's kind of a threshold effect
because there's a lot of you know
there's a lot of
dumb ideas that are circulated that only
bots
kick to each other but when you can get
a few humans to
to notice the conversation and and take
the forward the content without reading
it or without thinking about it
this is threshold effects then it
crosses over into human networks
of real users and that's what more
people are likely to see it
i don't know whether it takes there must
be some volume threshold if you buy
plenty of accounts and set them up
quickly
you may cross that threshold pretty
quickly but i don't know which um which
strategy is actually more effective
it all depends on the nature of network
propagation you know at the santa fe
institute where
i've been involved for many years some
of our researchers
study propagation on networks and
it's very very subtle you can simulate
it which is kind of fun right you can
make the following assumptions about how
the network is connected and how people
pass things along
or not and there's typically a either it
goes viral or it doesn't right so called
phase change or bifurcation point
and one could imagine either strategy
working depending on
the nature of the payload and the nature
of the network and how it's connected
and how it filters
so it's kind of very interesting problem
i suppose today people are just solving
it empirically by trying things and see
what works and then
tune and tune and tune but if one got to
be
able to actually build predictive models
we'll talk about a little bit later
one could in an automated fashion create
content specifically to take advantage
of the network propagation attributes
absolutely
and that's something that's i think
easier on twitter because twitter has
an open api right a programming
interface that lets
us pull raw data and with twitter you
can you can see
social networks you can see the
structure of who's following and who's
who's followed by
you know everybody else and that lets
you see
when a a message gets posted who
retweets it how quickly
and what edits are made and so you can
do that kind of analysis
over twitter it's much harder to do over
any social other social media platform
just because they don't
you can do it on reddit i'm sorry you
can do it on reddit
it's much harder to do on platforms
other than twitter and reddit
they just those platforms just don't
share yeah i did quite a bit of analysis
on reddit i don't know two or three
years ago where i sucked down all the
content on the donald
and analyzed it in various ways and it
was actually fun
and i thought it was a good thing that
that was available i could actually
track memes in their early days of
getting up regulated and predict what
memes might
go viral i probably had about a 50
percent chance on it which was way
better than most people
so yeah that transparency of data is
useful in certain ways but can be
misused in others
now let's switch directions a little bit
in your view and you seem to be the man
i mean you're the internet dude at
oxford
how critical is the internet these days
in electioneering
you know i note that trump has hired his
2016 social media dude as his campaign
manager
and here's another just sort of
interesting thing i couldn't remember
his name so i typed into google
brexit internet genius and of course it
came back with dominic cummings
and i particularly love was a headline
from the guardian that was titled
dominant cummings brilliant eccentric or
evil genius well guess what
dominic cummings is now one of the key
advisors
in general to the uk government so
in your view how critical is the
internet
in electioneering and the political
technical process today versus
everything else well i obviously i think
it's critical and i don't think
it makes sense to talk about modern
politics much without some appreciation
for how that
how the technical system the technical
features of the internet work
it's hard to imagine a modern political
candidate winning office
without a sophisticated digital media
strategy
in a lot of political campaigns now used
used to be that the
most important technical side of the
house was the
um was the pollster right the pollster
in richard vigory's day the the pollster
was the one who ran all the
communications side of things the web
where the webmaster reported to the
pollster and the
digital strategist reported to the
pollster let's switch now and now it's
often
the webmaster the digital campaign
strategist who manages
all the other technical resources so you
know
i don't think you can win without a
savvy a tech savvy strategy
and today that means having an instagram
campaign and a tick tock strategy and a
tinder strategy if you if you need it
that's where you think your voters are
that's where you need to be with a
digital strategy
interesting yeah i just looked it up
because i was curious what the experts
think about where the dollars are going
to go
and something on forbes recent
guesstimate was that
in the us 2020 elections probably 47
percent of the dollars will still go on
tv advertising
it's actually more than that so i think
you're instinctively right
that the television advertising still is
80 or 90 percent of a presidential
campaign's
buys and those are million dollar ad ad
buys with very
posh very high production value campaign
ads
that's the bulk of the expenditure i
would wonder
whether the television ad buys
could stand alone without a savvy
internet campaign
i would also bet that the internet
infrastructure
that gives a digital strategist
a sense of who's in which tv ad markets
is actually vital now no presidential
campaign covers the entire country
with exactly the same ad they rely on
the supply of data from their own
analytics firms
to figure out which ads need to include
which messages and they run them
in specific tv ad markets so
i totally buy the argument that the bulk
of the money goes to broadcast tv
but i do think it's much more
strategically those purchases are a lot
more strategic now
and the strategy comes comes from big
data that
mostly gets collected over the internet
that's a good point i hadn't really
focused on the fact that the two
together
operate synergistically right if you can
pre-test
memes pre-test images pre-test video
even
on the internet then you can probably do
a better job of targeting your tv okay
actually i read the
article quickly and it's approximately
75 tv
20 digital 5 radio is a reasonable
way of looking at what the experts think
in the 2020 campaign so that corresponds
pretty closely to your 20
guesstimate the next step up in your
building of your
argument from lies to lie machines to
computational propaganda
and there you talk about a quite
interesting network of networks
and one of the things i found
particularly interesting i never would
have thought of you gave an example
of tinder even being used as part of a
network of networks could you
talk a little bit about you know the
highest level framework of multi-network
feeds of junk news tinder facebook
instagram
provide a systematic view if you could i
call it computational propaganda
because that refers to the the fake news
and the the political lies
along with the computational systems
that take data from your credit card
or location data from your mobile phone
and figures out
a little bit more about who you are and
what you're likely to respond to
that's computationally intensive work
with a tinder example it's sort of a fun
example we caught
in the uk election three years ago 2019
two years ago where some campaign
managers
hired some creative programmers to
create
fake tinder profiles who would flirt
and then talk about jeremy corbyn and
the only reason we know about it is
because
the campaign managers who created the
tinderbots went on to twitter
the night after the election and thanked
their tinderbot
and named the districts where they
thought the tinderbot had given them a
few percentage points
you know advantage and and helped their
candidate win and i think the
the important the punch line in this
case the punchline of this example
is that the computational propaganda
doesn't need to reach everyone
it it doesn't reach all voters across
the country
it drills down into swing states or
districts where the vote's going to be
really close
and you know one percent two percent
makes a difference between who wins
and that's what makes it sort of
pernicious too because the
the messages that go into those narrow
districts or in particular states
aren't seen by the rest of the country
they aren't seen by the neighboring
neighboring communities
and of course that was true of direct
mail also you could micro target your
message
though it is true that facebook for
instance does have an archive of all
political messages one of the things
they do tell you when you sign up to be
a political advertiser if you run a
political ad it'll end up in their
political archive
but the reality is only researchers ever
take the time to look at that
that's true but there's a couple of
caveats i'd say there facebook only
recently made it possible to get access
to the
that archive and it's not easy
to get access to the archive so there
are hoops to jump for it's
not for all researchers and then they
only do that for a few countries in the
around the world i know they do it for
the us it's up and running now and it's
accessible
we think it includes most political ads
but if somebody hasn't gone through the
process you went through
hasn't self-declared as a as a political
advertiser
but is putting up political content that
content won't be in the archive
and then there are other democracies
around the world where um
you know elections run and facebook
doesn't provide the service
so um i think you know the large
technology firms definitely have
obligations to serve the voters in the
u.s you know the country where they were
born as firms
but there's a large number of other
democracies that deserve the same
same level of attention that's a good
point and the other one
is that merely a repository of data
doesn't do anybody any good unless
somebody does something with it so i
would call out to some investigative
journalists with a big budget let's say
the new york times or the wall street
journal
they're really ought to have somebody on
that beat going through those ads and
seeing if you can
surface what games people are playing i
mean individual citizen can't do it
and even a you know small academic
research organization probably have a
hard time doing it but the wall street
journal new york times they could do it
that's their job
guys get on it and most of the big media
outlets these days have some kind of
data science team
it's really hard to do good journalism
now without doing
what actually what they call
computational journalism sifting through
the big
big data that comes out of government
offices and the big technology firms and
looking for stories
yeah that's uh that's an important
feature of modern journalism and i bet
it'll be important for 2020 for covering
the 2020 election
yeah i hope somebody does that before
the election and says all right here are
the games both sides are playing with
they'll tell this message to this guy
and this message to that guy
right catch them out yep catch them out
and talk about a little bit
if anybody cares i suspect that's going
to seem like inside baseball and most
people aren't going to care but at least
it'd be nice to have some good eyes on
it
one final thing before we switch we're
getting short on time here on
some proposed remedies is an important
thing that you
talk about several times is that not
only is computational propaganda
used to push ideas and advocate for
candidates but it's often used to
generally disrupt conversations just
increase
noise and to suppress voting or interest
in elections
at all could you talk about that a
little bit
well what we found from from several
strategies now
is that the the goal is rarely to get
one particular person elected especially
if
americans are the target or canadians or
australians usually the goal
is to confuse people to get people to
not vote for the most serious candidate
right so the russian strategy in 2016
was much more about taking hillary
clinton down
than it was about pushing trump up it
was much more about
provoking race and angry race
conversations and
polarizing people on free speech issues
the the
the goal there is a long-term
degradation in our ability to make
decisions
our ability to choose politicians who
believe in evidence right
if you want to bring down your enemy
government one of the best things you
can do is make sure they have lousy
leaders
it means they don't play with evidence
they don't use evidence they don't make
sound decisions
and i think that's what the you know the
existential threat to democracy is
with these these kinds of campaigns yep
and a group of folks that i work with on
the internet we call that the attack on
sense making
a society to succeed has to be able to
make sense of evidence right has to do
so in a high quality fashion
and this vast both intentional and
unintentional circulation of
misinformation
general stupidity insanity whatever you
want to call it
has without a doubt decreased our social
sense making capability and
a number of us believe frankly that
social media networks many to many
networks and their couplings between
networks and these cycles that we talked
about the chans and back up and down
may actually be overwhelming our
cognitive capability as individuals that
it's just beyond
the average person and probably even the
above average person's ability to make
sense of it
and that if we are going to try to make
sense we probably need to club together
into collective sense making in fact we
have a little trial
group on the internet called rally point
alpha on facebook if anyone wants to
join that's committed to trying to make
sense
and people post things and we comment
upon them and is this bullshit or is it
not
etc and i will say even as a person
who's pretty well
informed participating in rally point
alpha has been
a definite upgrade in my own ability to
make sense of the world
and you know that may be at least one
way for people to respond to
technologies and data sources frankly
that produce
results above the ability of a single
individual to even be able to understand
and deal with
yeah that that totally makes makes sense
to me i think looking around the world
the countries that seem to have been
slightly inoculated
against the effects of misinformation
are the countries that have
a national broadcaster now i don't mean
that these are countries where the
government owns the media
i mean countries where the government
where the public money is put into
something like
the bbc here in the uk or the cbc in the
us
australia has one too the countries that
have a public broadcaster
seem to have that what did you call it
that club effect
high quality professional news sorts out
the dreck
occasionally they make mistakes right
and there's always a little bit of bias
but it's not nearly as bad as some of
the other outlets
that work in modern journalism so
having a public broadcaster figure out
what what
the top three issues are that we really
need to be talking about right now
that's a vital part turns out that's a
vital part of modern democracy
and i think we've lost that when there's
so many different multi-various
sources of information some video some
text
some extremists and some you know
commentary masking is news
i think your instinct is right there's
probably too many sources
too many low quality or mixed message
sources
yeah we have to be able to curate the
information that we consume
and it may be beyond what us as
individuals can do and that you know
working together with a group of people
to
co-curate our information flows and
inform each other might be an answer
but let's go down to your answers the
last chapter in your book
you talk a fair amount about what you
think could be done
to level the playing field between the
cognitive ability of mere humans
and computational propaganda well the
the main idea the first the starting
point for this is figuring out ways is
trying to identify ways to prevent
the best information about public life
from being hoarded by a few private
firms in silicon valley
right now you know there was there was a
time when the library of congress was
the greatest library in the world and
the british library had data from
and data and evidence and public records
and everyone could go
research do research and build a
business uh come up with a new law
write a book um right now the highest
quality data about
our behavior and our attitudes and our
aspirations
sits in silicon valley and it's
privately held
so the basic institutional level change
has to be that some of that data gets
shared gets anonymized
gets distributed sits in the library of
congress or sits in the british library
so that
journalists and independent researchers
and faith-based charities
all sorts of civil society groups can
can have access to it can play with it
now getting there is going to be tough
and i think the the first step in
getting there
involves changing who our devices
report to right now when we buy a phone
or we put in a smart fridge or
put in some device in our home the data
that flows from that device
only goes to the owners of the networks
and we as users
we can't look at our phone and ask it to
tell us who's benefiting
from our data i think we need a rebuild
in the sense that we need to be able to
look at any device we're putting in our
home
and ask it to tell us who the ultimate
beneficiary
of our behavioral data is now once we
can get devices to do that simple step
who's who's benefiting from our data i
think we should be able to add
organizations to that list of
beneficiaries
because that way you know i think we
express ourselves civically
if i want to support my favorite coffee
collective
or i want to support a particular
politician or covid researchers
i would happily donate my family's day
well i would happily donate my data
to medical researchers if i thought it
would help with covert research
but i don't have that ability right now
so just
getting devices that are accountable and
then having the ability to add actors to
the list of beneficiaries
that's the big infrastructure change i
would like to see
how do you think that would really work
i don't know i mean isn't that just
adding more gasoline
to the wars for disinformation because
people
on the left some of them will give that
data to antifa
or to anarchists or marxist leninist
people on the right will
give that data to white supremacists to
white nationalists to other kinds of
crackpots
why do you think that will end up
improving discourse rather than just
adding gasoline to the fire
well i think it's maybe my answer by
metaphor would be
it'll make it a controlled fire in the
sense that
right now we have no sight of this i
don't think we can take away facebook
right we're not gonna we're not gonna
get rid of instagram we can't give up
twitter
we're not gonna take everybody's phones
back we can't get rid of social media
the best we can hope for is to to
rebuild right do a little rebuild
and try to change the flow of
information
now if there are white supremacists
making use of my behavioral data
the behavioral data from my credit cards
i want to know
and i would end that well i would choose
to end that relationship
right now as citizens you know most
people most of the time
wouldn't closely police where their data
is going
but if given the chance i would go
through the list of beneficiaries and i
would strike some out and i'd want to
add some too
that's i think the flow of data is
actually now our primary mode of
expressing expressing ourselves
politically we do whatever we vote
what every four or five years but every
day we generate tons of data
that goes off and as people make
political inferences from it
but we have no control over that process
that's a radical idea i'm still i'd say
i'm fairly skeptical
one whether it won't just make the
problem worse and two if people are
willing to do very much with it you know
for instance
both google and facebook have long
provided
the ability to see how you're defined in
their advertising databases according to
your areas of interest and all this sort
of stuff and you can even edit it out
right you know
they know for instance that you belong
to a hunting special interest group
and you can actually edit that out i
don't know one person in a hundred
who's ever looked at those ad profiles
and maybe one i i've looked at them
several times just because i'm
interested in such things but i've never
done anything about it right
do you really think anyone's going to
take the effort because you know my
model
someone who's been building online
products since 1980
is that what people really want is
appliances they don't
have any interest in fact quite the
opposite they don't want to have any of
their time or attention spent on
fiddle fucking with the details of their
appliances
and asking people to dig in like that
just strikes me is
very unrealistic well i think you're i
think your instinct is right that most
people most of the time
wouldn't care a lot about this they do
tend to care about these things
in the few days before people vote right
so in the week leading up to an election
that's when everybody's mind turns
around
comes around to you know who you're
voting for what's going on with my data
who has my records who has my voter
registration files
um i think right now even if we wanted
to
we we couldn't go around to all the
devices
aside from the examples you offered
google and facebook
we'd have to do that with every platform
we wouldn't have full control
we'd have no say in the data they've
already collected and already
distributed
and frankly if you try to do what you're
describing right if you try to to cut
back on your data flows
you'd get restricted services right
gmail wouldn't work
the way the way it should you wouldn't
have access
you wouldn't have the same internet
experience and now the firms will say
well
we need the data if you want that
internet experience but
i'm not sure that that's so true i think
a little bit more user control
would let us restore that high degree of
trust that we had 15 20 25 years ago yep
it's an interesting problem right
because as you point out
letting the services have details about
our user behavior
actually does provide for us benefits in
terms
of the products themselves for instance
i use this example
because i'm a technologist and still a
computer programmer
when i type python into a google search
it knows i'm talking about the computer
language not the snake
right and if i turned off history it
would not know that
right i have actually experimented with
turning history off on google or using
no history services like duckduckgo
much worse experience sorry right i also
experienced with turning off the zuck
algorithm on facebook which you can
still do
even though it's a pain in the ass and
it'll reset it about every 36 hours
and guess what the flow of information
is less interesting
and less appropriate than using the zuck
algorithm that's all about manipulating
our behavior
however i think there is a place where
you can
have the better products without the
misuse of the information
at least by paid actors and this is very
radical and this is something i've
talked with tristan harris about i think
he agrees in principle but he thinks
it's too radical
and that is to ban advertising period
for a long time the internet was not
mostly about advertising most products
in fact most of the products i built
were paid subscription products and
today with the low cost of platforms
those costs could be quite low people
don't probably quite have internalized
this yet
but the total revenue of facebook is
about two dollars per month per user
that's the revenue and we know they're
highly profitable
we also know a fair amount of their cost
is in their ad infrastructure
so i suspect that one could run a social
media platform for a buck or two
a month at you know 100 million person
scale almost all the economies of scale
are reached by 100 million
so today we could have alternative
business model
of very low monthly payments for these
big platforms i don't think anybody
would object to paying two dollars a
month at least in the united states or
in the west a subscription box
yes yeah think about this the incentives
are suddenly reversed
in a ad driven model they have every
incentive to keep you on
as long as possible so they get you they
pull you into arguments
it up regulates the most controversial
shit that you'll send to other people to
start more arguments
so their incentives to keep you on as
long as possible if it's a subscription
model say two bucks a month
guess what their incentives are exactly
reversed they want to provide as much
value to you
so you'll stay a subscriber in as short
a time as possible so you'll
expend the least amount of their
computational resources
so suddenly your values and their values
are in alignment rather than today
where you don't want your attention to
be hijacked but their economic
incentives
is to not only hijack it at the micro
scale but at the macro scale by
circulating inflammatory rhetoric
so i continue to believe that is the
silver bullet
have our social media but convert it to
a modest
monthly subscription fee i think that
one of the other advantages of the the
monthly subscription model
is that you i think you'd get more
competition
you'd get other businesses saying that
they could deliver better services
or slightly less expensive and you might
yeah you might
might get some diversity in in the
platforms there
absolutely and it's true that
advertising is now micro targeted but
the biggest advertisers still want to
buy in bulk
and so it's easier to convince
individuals of a value proposition than
it is you know they try to get the
interest of the unilevers or the procter
and gambles to advertise on one's little
startup platform so
i think you hit on it exactly right this
would provide an ecosystem
that allowed more competition well this
has been an interesting conversation
philip i have to say this is an area of
huge importance
for you know all citizens everywhere in
the world i'd encourage those who want
to learn more about it to read philip's
very interesting book called lie
machines
thank you very much for being on the
show thanks for a great conversation jim
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared janes consulting
music by tom muller at
modernspacemusic.com